A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of Elinor Barber FA632
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Subject Files, 1967 - 1981; II
  - Education, B
    - Language Education, 1979 - 1980 (Box 12, Folder 180)
    - Language Education, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 181)
    - Language Education, 1976- 1977 (Box 12, Folder 182)
    - Language Education, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 183)
    - Language Education, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 184)
    - Language Education, 1971 - 1973 (Box 12, Folder 185)
    - Language Education, 1969 - 1970 (Box 12, Folder 186)
    - Language Education, 1967 - 1968 (Box 12, Folder 187)
    - Sex Differences in Education - EGB Paper, Recipients' Responses, 1978 - 1979 (Box 13, Folder 188)
    - Sex Differences in Education - EGB Paper, Recipients' Responses, 1977 July - December (Box 13, Folder 189)
    - Sex Differences in Education - EGB Paper, Recipients' Responses, 1977 May - June (Box 13, Folder 190)
    - Sex Differences in Education - Meeting, Feb. 5, 1979, 1978 - 1979 (Box 13, Folder 191)
    - Rural Education, 1979 - 1980 (Box 13, Folder 192)
    - Rural Education (IIEP Seminar), 1975 - 1979 (Box 13, Folder 193)
    - HE&R Office Activities, 1975 - 1979 (Box 13, Folder 194)
    - HE&R Office Activities, 1970 - 1974 (Box 13, Folder 195)
    - March 1981 Information Paper - Education, 1980 - 1981 (Box 13, Folder 196)
- Appendix A: Reports by Elinor Barber
  - Information paper: international programs related to the status, roles, and opportunities of women, 1975 August (Report 2066)
  - Some perspectives on sex differences in education, 1977 May (Report 6114)
  - The International Division Women's Program: interim report, 1977 March (Report 6123)
  - Interim report and initial recommendations of the Committee on Women in International Division Programs, 1974 September (Report 7004)
  - Visit to Stanford and Berkeley, 1977 October (Report 7558)
  - Mexican visit, May - June 1979, 1979 July (Report 7692)
  - Asian trip, 1978 March (Report 7739)
  - Visit to Kenya and Tanzania, 1976 December (Report 7741)
  - Visit to England, 1976 October (Report 7742)
  - Visit to some women activists and researchers in Italy, 1976 October (Report 7743)
  - Program opportunities and program possibilities in the field of women's rights, opportunities, or disabilities, 1973 January (Report 7749)
  - Perspectives of the International Division on program activities bearing on the status of women, 1972 May (Report 7750)
  - (EGB version of meeting 11/17/71 on Women in Higher Education) (Report 7751)
  - Affirmative Action: the need for self-study, 1973 December (Report 7752)
  - The status and roles of women as related to and affected by the programs of the International Division, 1974 April (Report 7771)
  - Conference on "Le Fait Feminin", 1976 September (Report 7772)
  - IIEP Seminar on Inequalities in the Development of Education, 1978 December (Report 7773)
  - International Sociological Association meetings, 1978 September (Report 7774)
  - Conference on Equal Pay and Equal Opportunity at Wellesley College, 1978 May (Report 7775)
  - National Women's Conference, 1977 December (Report 7776)
  - Visit to Radcliffe Institute, 1975 December (Report 7777)
  - Visit to Wellesley Center, 1975 December (Report 7778)
  - AID Conference on Women in Development, 1975 November (Report 7779)
  - Wellesley and Wingspread Conferences, 1976 June (Report 7780)
  - Seminar on African Women in Rural Development, 1976 May (Report 7781)
  - The Percy Amendment, 1974 May (Report 7789)
  - Curriculum for professionals dealing with rural women, 1980 December (Report 7839)
  - Visit to India and Indonesia, 1981 April (Report 7857)
  - The Brazilian women's program, 1980 April (Report 7860)
  - Discussions in Paris of research on women, 1976 September (Report 7867)
  - Trip to Colombia and Brazil, 1974 July (Report 7868)
  - Visits to Berkeley and Stanford, 1976 March (Report 7872)
  - Trip to the Philippines, Pakistan, Bangladesh and India - March, 1975, 1975 May (Report 7880)
  - The International Division Women's Program - Information Paper, 1979 January (Report 7889)
  - Visit to Nigeria, Nov. 3 - 10, 1976, 1976 December (Report 7910)
  - Impressions of the status of women in Japan (Report 7915)
  - West Africa visit, February 1980, 1980 April (Report 7925)
  - The sociolinguistics scene, 1977 October (Report 7996)
  - (Access to women's education in rural areas), 1979 December (Report 7997)
  - Rural education, 1979 October (Report 7998)
  - Barbara Burn's Meeting on Advanced Training and Research, 1978 November (Report 8000)
  - Copenhagen Forum, 1980 July (Report 8157)
  - Visit to the Center, May 18 and 19, 1987 June (Report 8163)
  - Meeting on Language, 1971 June (Report 8166)
  - Conference on Sociolinguistics Surveys, 1975 May (Report 8222)
  - The International Division Women's Program - information paper, 1979 January (Report 8229)
- Appendix B: Reports: Women's Status/Roles/Opportunities
  - Affirmative action program for the employment of women and minorities on the professional staff of the Ford Foundation: a review and analysis, 1974 February (Report 1984)
  - Peterson, Esther. Long overdue- full partnership for women in American society, 1971 October (Report 1991)
  - Bundy, McGeorge. Affirmative action and Foundation grantees (Report 1994)
  - Trottenberg, Arthur D. An affirmative action program for the employment of women and minorities on the professional staff, 1972 July (Report 1995)
  - Bundy, McGeorge. An affirmative action program for the employment of women and minorities on the professional staff, 1972 July (Report 1996)
  - Bundy, McGeorge. Affirmative action, 1974 January (Report 1997)
  - External affirmative action initiative- a review of the first 18 months, 1975 June (Report 2028)
  - Background material. Affirmative action, 1975 July (Report 2034)
  - Anderson, Kristin. A report of television and radio programming for women and children in the Middle East, 1975 July (Report 2043)
  - Barber, Elinor G. International programs related to the status, roles, and opportunities of women, 1975 November (Report 2066)
  - Katzowitz, Lauren. Report of the Ford Foundation Conference on Women and Public Employment, 1975 February (Report 2107)
  - Smith, Theodore M. Proposal: an internal internship program for the Ford Foundation, 1974 May (Report 2136)
  - External Affirmative Action Program, 1975 October (Report 2137)
  - Lindenbaum, Shirley. The social and economic status of women in Bangladesh (Report 2180)
  - Jahan, Rounaq. Women in Bangladesh, 1974 February (Report 2185)
  - Abdullah, Tahrunessa A. Village women as I saw them, 1974 May (Report 2186)
  - Sattar, Ellen. Women in Bangladesh: a village study, 1974 October (Report 2190)
  - External Affirmative Action program, 1975 October (Report 2196)
  - The Ford Foundation's program in the changing roles of women, 1973 March (Report 2255)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Final report: consultancy on women in Bangladesh, 1975 December (Report 2281)
  - Coordinating Committee for Women's Programs. Report to the President, 1975 January (Report 2326)
  - Katzowitz, Lauren. The Equal Rights Amendment: a discussion (Report 2641)
  - Recommendations for women's programs, 1971 October (Report 2659)
  - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs. 1975 report to the President, 1976 June (Report 2945)
  - Subcommittee on Affirmative Action. Report of the Subcommittee on Affirmative Action, 1975 December (Report 3129)
  - Women's Law Program: litigation and monitoring, 1975 July (Report 3176)
  - Germain, Adrienne. World Conference of the International Women's Year, 1975 August (Report 3424)
  - Kanter, Rosabeth M. et al. Review of grant-making for women's issues in the 197O's: past patterns and future priorities, 1977 April (Report 3505)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Women's roles in Bangladesh development: a program assessment, 1976 April (Report 3708)
  - Chen, Marty et al. Rural women in Bangladesh: exploding some myths, 1976 May (Report 3710)
  - Abdullah/Zeidenstein. Finding ways to learn about rural women: experiences from a pilot project in Bangladesh, 1976 November (Report 3933)
  - Hamilton, Muriel. Education for women and children in Pakistan, 1974 August (Report 3934)
  - Puryear, J. M. Sex discrimination in education: alternative approaches for the International Division's Women's Programs, 1980 March (Report 3959)
  - Saario, Terry. The Education and Research Division's program on sex discrimination and equality of opportunity for women, 1978 March (Report 4136)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Consultancy on women's status and roles in India, February 4-17, 1976, 1976 March (Report 4249)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Women in development: final consultancy report, February 17-April 3, 1976, 1976 April (Report 4250)
  - Oppong, Christine. Workplan for a review of women's status in West Africa, 1976 September (Report 4384)
  - Ford Foundation. Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs: a report to the President, 1978 June (Report 4439)
  - Grey, Audrey Ward. Childhood, children and child-rearing in the Arab Middle East-- a selected and annotated bibliography, 1973 March (Report 4527)
  - Ford Foundation. Survey of foundation and government grants for women's rights and opportunities, 1971-1975, 1975 November (Report 4542)
  - Albert, Judith D. Women, 1977 October (Report 4571)
  - Ford Foundation programs for women, 1979 December (Report 4641)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Women in development: final consultancy report, August 27- Sept. 10, 1976, 1976 September (Report 4645)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Women in development: final consultancy report, 1977 March 8 - April 20 (Report 4646)
  - Germain, Adrienne et al. Food, employment, and the role of women in Indonesia (Report 4647)
  - Ford Foundation programs for women - plans and budgets for fiscal years 1980 and 1981, 1980 March (Report 4793)
  - National Manpower Institute. Survey of federal government grants and contracts focusing on women's rights and opportunities 1971-1976, 1977 March (Report 4921)
  - Bellamy, Blank, Goodman, Kelly and Stanley. Affirmative action in practice: a preliminary report to the Ford Foundation, 1975 February (Report 4966)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Consultancy on women's roles in development, August 13-27, 1976, Pakistan, 1976 September (Report 5004)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Consultancy on Brazilian women's roles in development, June 20-July 9, 1976, 1976 August (Report 5005)
  - Germain, Adrienne. The new home economics: insights on development problems, 1976 December (Report 5006)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Women and national development policy: issues to consider in the Sudan, 1976 January (Report 5007)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Poor women: a new feminist view, 1975 May (Report 5008)
  - Germain, Adrienne. The status and roles of Ghanaian and Kenyan women: implications for fertility behavior, 1974 (Report 5009)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Some aspects of the roles of women in population and development, 1974 January (Report 5010)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Fertility control in the Third World: where do we go from here?, 1973 February (Report 5011)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Analysis of sex differentials in 1976-77 Egyptian farm management survey data: review of my consultancy, 1979 March (Report 5012)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Symposium on the changing status of Sudanese women, February 23-March 1, 1979, 1979 March (Report 5013)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Economic growth, household production strategies and sex differentiation of wage rates and productive work opportunities: the case of Thailand, 1978 October (Report 5014)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Consultancy on women's roles in Mexican development, June 1-10, 1977, 1977 July (Report 5015)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Consultancy on the roles and status of women in Jamaica, 1977 February (Report 5016)
  - Dixon, Ruth B. Programming for women in the Ford Foundation, Bangladesh: report of a consultancy, 1980 May 19 - June 19 (Report 5074)
  - Manoff International Inc. Report to the Ford Foundation of Manoff International Inc. mission to UNECA's Africa Training and Research Center for Women, Oct. 11 to Nov. 3, 1976, 1976 December (Report 5665)
  - Dixon, Ruth B. Jobs for women in rural industry and services, 1980 October (Report 5685)
  - Germain, Adrienne/Barber, Elinor G. Next steps regarding the Division's program for women, 1979 December (Report 5696)
  - Bell, David E. Next steps regarding the Division's program for women, 1980 January (Report 5697)
  - Cool, John. The social dynamics of the feminine renaissance: a tentative framework for analysis. (Report 5698)
  - Dirasse, Laketch. Preliminary plans and budget estimates for expanded women's programs in Eastern and Southern Africa, 1980 January (Report 5699)
  - Fuller, William. Programs for women, 1980 January (Report 5700)
  - Flora, Cornelia Butler. Women and the future: the need for a new model, 1980 January (Report 5701)
  - Dye, Richard W. Expanded women's program estimates: Andes and the Southern Cone, 1980 January (Report 5702)
  - Flora, Cornelia B./Myers, Robert G. Preproposal. (Report 5703)
  - Gardner, James A. Women's programs in Brazil, 1980 January (Report 5704)
  - Flora, Cornelia B. Recommendation for "A" status: proposed FY1980 activities on women and development, 1980 January (Report 5705)
  - Kessinger, Tom G. Jakarta office submission for women's program, 1980 February (Report 5706)
  - Pande, Vijay G. Request for new funds for the India office program for women, 1980 February (Report 5708)
  - McKee, Katharine. Indicative planning for expanded women's program in West and Central Africa, 1980 February (Report 5709)
  - Shaw, Robert D'Arcy. Possible women's programs in Pakistan, 1980 February (Report 5710)
  - Cool, John C. David Bell's January 3rd memo on the Division's program for women, 1980 February (Report 5711)
  - Gardner, James A. Women, social change and human choice, some general thoughts, 1980 February (Report 5712)
  - De Spoelberch, Guillaume/Robarts, Richard C. Women's programming, 1980 February (Report 5713)
  - Puryear, Jeffrey M. Women's program estimates: the Caribbean, 1980 February (Report 5714)
  - Geithner, Peter F. Next steps regarding the Division's program for women, 1980 February (Report 5715)
  - McKee, Katharine. Initial comments on exploration of the long-term implications of rapidly changing sex roles, 1980 February (Report 5716)
  - Harkavy, Oscar. Notes for commments on H/N/P and women's programs, 1980 March (Report 5717)
  - Zeidenstein, Sondra and Laura. Observations on the status of women in Bangladesh, 1973 May (Report 5779)
  - Zeidenstein, Sondra. Report on the first two years of the IRDP pilot project on population planning and rural women's cooperatives, 1976 June (Report 5780)
  - Murthy, Nirmala. A study of Lijjat Papad-- a women's organization, 1978 May (Report 5782)
  - Mayo, Molly. Women's organizations in Pakistan-- a preliminary identification, 1976 January (Report 5784)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Rural production, employment problems and sex differentiation of wage rates and productive work opportunities: a policy research agenda, 1978 May (Report 5786)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Current status of Lagos office programs in support of women, 1980 November (Report 5787)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Review of grant (77-563) to the Jamaica Women's Bureau (Report 5788)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Women in Nepal, 1976 September (Report 5789)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Research on women in agricultural production in the Third World, 1980 April (Report 5790)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Report on consultancy, women's programming, June 1-23, 1978, 1978 June (Report 5792)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Presentation to a luncheon seminar at the International Institute for the Study of Human Reproduction, Center for Population and Family Health, Columbia University, 1976 November 10 (Report 5793)
  - Germain, Adrienne. Summary of interviews on the status of women in the Philippines, 1973 June (Report 5796)
  - Engle, Patricia Lee. The intersecting needs of working women and their young children: a report to the Ford Foundation, 1980 August (Report 5797)
  - Pfanner, David. The status of women in Thailand, 1972 October (Report 5947)
  - Drake Beam & Associates. Attitude survey concerning the role of women at the Ford Foundation, 1970 December (Report 6002)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Trip to the Philippines, Pakistan, Bangladesh, and India - March, 1975, 1975 May (Report 6113)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Some perspectives on sex differences in education, 1977 May (Report 6114)
  - Barber, Elinor G. The International Division's Women's Program: interim report, 1977 March (Report 6123)
  - Bell, David E. Draft materials on expanded programs for women, 1980 February (Report 6263)
  - Trottenberg, Arthur D. The role of women in the Ford Foundation, 1971 June (Report 6316)
  - Cole, Jonathan R. Affirmative action policy: problematics and proposals, 1974 (Report 6355)
  - Berresford, Susan. Trip report on Colombia and Peru, 1980 July (Report 6396)
  - Carden, Maren Lockwood. Feminism in 1975: the non-establishment, the establishment, and the future, 1976 March (Report 6507)
  - Ford Foundation. The Equal Rights Amendment: a discussion (Report 6515)
  - Manitzas, Nita Rous. Conference on "Feminine perspectives in social science research in Latin America", March 18-23, 1974, 1974 April (Report 6612)
  - Harris, Rosalind W. Survey of rural funding for the advancement of women (Report 6814)
  - Flora, Cornelia Butler. Women in Venezuela, 1980 November (Report 6823)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Interim report and initial recommendations of the Committee on Women in International Division programs, 1974 September (Report 7004)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Program concerns in the International Division with regard to the rights and opportunities of women, 1973 November (Report 7006)
  - Bundy, McGeorge. External affirmative action initiative, 1975 October (Report 7007)
  - Smock, Audrey Chapman. Women's opportunities for education and its impact on their roles in Kenya. (Report 7008)
  - Miller, Frank J. The women of Pakistan, 1972 December (Report 7009)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Recent activity on the international front, 1972 November (Report 7010)
  - Peet, Creighton. Review of research on women in agricultural development, 1980 July (Report 7012)
  - Berresford, Susan. Six-month report from the Women's Program Group, 1980 July (Report 7013)
  - Caughman, Susan. Women at work in Mali: the case of the Markala Cooperative, 1980 November (Report 7016)
  - Mayo, Molly. Women in their society: a selected bibliography of Pakistan and other Islamic countries, 1976 January (Report 7276)
  - Redclift, Nanneke Codd. Women's programs in Nicaragua, 1979 December (Report 7304)
  - Sandler, Jerrold and Bernice. Possible uses of telecommunications to meet the educational needs of women, 1973 March (Report 7313)
  - Carden, Maren Lockwood. The new feminist movement in the U.S.: 1975, 1975 December (Report 7393)
  - Pinto, Francoise Latour. Report to the Ford Eoundation, 5-17 February 1970, 1979 March (Report 7552)
  - Saario, Terry Tinson. Mirrors, prisms, and magnifying glasses: an assessment of women's rights in education, 1979 April (Report 7553)
  - Elmendorf, Mary. Summary report and recommendations, 1973 December (Report 7556)
  - Elmendorf, Mary. La campesina indigena. (Report 7557)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Visit to Stanford and Berkeley, 1977 October (Report 7558)
  - Spatta, Carolyn D. An inventory of women's studies programs and women's research centers in Asia, Africa, the Middle East and Latin America, 1980 February (Report 7683)
  - Ford Foundation. Ford Foundation Conference on Women and Public Employment-- background paper, 1975 February (Report 7678)
  - Islam, Shamima. Rural women in Bangladesh: socio-economic conditions and educational needs, 1979 June (Report 7682)
  - Sundar, Pushpa. Credit and finance needs of women workers (Report 7684)
  - Sundar, Pushpa. Working Women's Forum, Madras, 1979 March (Report 7685)
  - Hertz, Willard. The Foundation's External Affirmative Action Program, 1979 August (Report 7686)
  - Saario, Terry. Sexism, inequality, and education, 1978 May (Report 7687)
  - Jones, Sidney. Islamic education in Indonesia, 1979 (Report 7688)
  - Jaffe, Natalie. The pioneers: women fight for parity in the bluecollar work force, 1980 April (Report 7689)
  - Silverstein, Leni M. Women's programs in Sao Paulo, consultancy report, 1980 January (Report 7690)
  - Elmendorf, Mary. Projects involving women in Mexico, 1973 August (Report 7691)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Mexican visit, May-June 1979, 1979 July (Report 7692)
  - Flora, Cornelia Butler. Trip to the Dominican Republic, 1980 September (Report 7693)
  - Flora, Cornelia Butler. Women and rural development: the shift to capitalist production and the formation of a female proletariat. (Report 7694)
  - Barroso, Carmen. The United Nations Conference - Women's Half Decade Forum - Copenhagen, July 14-24, 1980 - narrative report. (Report 7697)
  - Redclift, Nanneke Codd. Centro de Apoyo a las Mujeres Violadas, 1979 November (Report 7698)
  - Redclift, Nanneke Codd. "Gente Ayudando Gente": community development projects in Yucatan, 1979 December (Report 7699)
  - McKee, Katharine. Background information in support of proposed planning, training and research DAP on West Africa women's roles and status, 1977 February (Report 7700)
  - Knight, Lucy. Report of meeting on Women in Higher Education, 1977 February (Report 7703)
  - Knight, Lucy. Minutes of meeting on Women in Higher Education, 1977 February (Report 7704)
  - Smock, Audrey Chapman. Report on my consultancy, 1979 May (Report 7709)
  - Fox, Lynn H. The problem of women and mathematics, 1980 March (Report 7724)
  - Smock, Audrey Chapman. Education 1976: status report, 1977 October (Report 7727)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Asia trip, 1978 March (Report 7739)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Visit to Kenya and Tanzania, 1976 December (Report 7741)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Visit to England, 1976 October (Report 7742)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Visit to some women activists and researchers in Italy, 1976 October (Report 7743)
  - Smock, Audrey C. The impact of education on women's roles: the case of Ghana (Report 7744)
  - Smock, Audrey C. Sex differences in educational opportunity and employment in six countries, 1978 October (Report 7745)
  - Smock, Audrey C. Women's access to education and its impact on their roles in Mexico (Report 7746)
  - The International Division's Women's Program - discussion paper, 1976 (Report 7747)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Program activities and program possibilities in the field of women's rights, opportunities, or disabilities, 1973 January (Report 7749)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Perspectives of the International Division on program activities bearing on the status of women, 1972 May (Report 7750)
  - Barber, Elinor G. (EGB version of meeting 11/17/71 on Women in Higher Education), 1971 November 17 (Report 7751)
  - Barber, Elinor G./Smith, Theodore M. Affirmative action: the need for self-study, 1973 December (Report 7752)
  - Women's Program Group. The Affirmative Action Personnel Program, 1973 June (Report 7754)
  - Hertz, Willard J. External affirmative action, 1975 April (Report 7770)
  - Barber, Elinor G./Germain, Adrienne. The status and roles of women as related to and affected by the programs of the International Division, 1976 April (Report 7771)
  - Barber, Elinor G./Saario, Terry. Conference on "Le Fait Feminin", 1976 September (Report 7772)
  - Barber, Elinor G. IIEP Seminar on inequalities in the development of education, 1978 December (Report 7773)
  - Barber, Elinor G. International Sociological Association meetings, 1978 September (Report 7774)
  - Barber, Elinor G. Conference on Equal Pay and Equal Opportunity at Wellesley College, 1978 May (Report 7775)
  - Barber, Elinor G. National Women's Conference, 1977 December (Report 7776)